sound. CHAPTER 14 A YOUNG Raja The mo was hidden in mist when the
morning came and the rain had not stopped pouring down. There could be no
going out of doors. Martha was so busy that Mary had no opportunity of talking
to her, but in the afternoon she asked her to come and sit with her in the
nursery. She came bringing the stocking she was always knitting when she was doing nothing
else. "What's the matter with thee?" she asked as soon as they sat down that
looks as if that's something to say." "I have. I have found out what the crying
was," said Mary. Martha let her knitting drop on her knee and gazed at her with startled eyes
there hasn't!" she exclaimed. "Never!" "I heard it in the night," Mary went on. "And I got
up and went to see where it came from. It was Colin. I found
him." Martha's face became red with fright. "Eh! Miss Mary!" she said half crying
thou shouldn't have done it thou shouldn't thou get me in trouble. I never
told thee nothing about him— —but thou get me in trouble. I shall lose my place and
what will mother do!" "You won't lose your place," said Mary. "He was glad I came. We
talked and talked and he said he was glad I came." "Was he?" cried Martha. "Art that
sure that doesn't know what he's like when anything vexes him. He's a big lad
to cry like a baby, but when he's in a passion he'll Faire scream just to
frighten us. He knows us D call our souls our own." "He wasn't vexed," said
Mary. "I asked him if I should go away and he made me
stay. He asked me questions and I sat on a big foot stol and talked to him about
India and about the robin and gardens. He wouldn't let me go. He let me see his
mother's picture. Before I left him I sang him to sleep." Martha fairly gasped with
amazement. "I can scarcely believe thee!"
she protested. "It's as if the walked straight into a lion's den. If he'd been
like he is most times he'd have throwed himself into one of his tantrums and
Rouse the house. He won't let strangers look at him." "He let me look at him. I
looked at him all the time and he looked at me. We stared!" said Mary. "I don't know
what to do!" cried agitated Martha. "If Mrs.
Medlock finds out, she'll think I broke orders and told thee and I shall be
packed back to mother."
"He is not going to tell Mrs. Medlock anything about it yet. It's to be a sort
of secret just at first," said Mary firmly. "And he says everybody is obliged to do as he
pleases I that's true enough the bad lad!"
sighed Martha, wiping her forehead with her apron. "He says Mrs. Medlock must. And
he wants me to come and talk to him
every day. And you are to tell me when he wants me."
"Me me said Martha; I shall lose my place— —I shall for
sure!" "You can't if you are doing what he wants you to do and everybody is ordered
to obey him," Mary argued. "Does that mean to say," cried
Martha with wide open eyes, "that he was nice to thee!" "I think he almost liked me," Mary
answered. "Then thou must have bewitched him!" decided Martha, drawing a long breath.
"Do you mean Magic?" inquired Mary. "I've heard about Magic in India, but I can't
make it. I just went into his room and I
was so surprised to see him I stood and stared. And then he turned around and
stared at me. And he thought I was a ghost or a dream and I thought perhaps he
was. And it was so queer being there alone together in the middle of the
night and not knowing about each other.
And we began to ask each other questions
s And when I asked him if I must go away he said I must
not the world's coming to an end!" gasped Martha. "What is the matter with him?" asked
Mary. "Nobody knows for sure and certain," said Martha. "Mr. Craven went off his head
like when he was born the doctors thought he'd have to be put in a silem
It was because Mrs. Craven died like I told you. He wouldn't set eyes on on the
baby. He just raved and said it'd be another hunchback like him and it had better
die." "Is Callin a hunchback?" Mary asked. "He didn't look like
one." "He isn't yet," said Martha. "But he began all wrong. Mother said that there
was enough trouble and raging in the house to set any child wrong. They was
afraid his back was weak and they've always been taken care of it keeping him
lying down and not letting him walk.
Once they made him wear a brace but he feted so he was downright ill. Then a big
doctor came to see him and made them take it off. He talked to the other
doctor quite rough— —in a polite way. He said there'd been too much medicine and
too much letting him have his own way." "I think he's a very spoiled boy," said
Mary. "He's the worst young now as ever was!" said
Martha. "I won't say as he hasn't been ill a good bit. He's had coughs and colds
that's nearly killed him two or three times. Once he had rheumatic fever and once he had
typhoid hey Mrs. Medlock did get a fright then. He'd been out of his head and she
was talking to the nurse thinking he didn't know nothing and she said, 'He'll
die this time sure enough and best thing for him and for everybody and she looked
at him and there he was with his big eyes open staring at her as sensible as
she was herself. She didn't know what had happen but he just stared at her and
says, 'You give me some water and stop talking Do you think he will die?" asked
Mary. "Mother says there's no reason why any child should live that gets no fresh
air and doesn't do nothing but lie on his back and read picture books and take
medicine. He's weak and hates the trouble of being taken out of doors and he gets
cold so easy he says it makes him ill." Mary sat and looked at the
fire. "I wonder," she said slowly, "if it would not do him good to go out into a
garden and watch things growing. It did me good." "One of the worst fits he ever had,"
said Martha, "was one time they took him out where the roses is by the
fountain. He'd been reading in a paper about people getting something he called
'rose cold and he began to sneeze and said he'd got it and then a new gardener
as didn't know the rules passed by and looked at him curious. He threw himself
into a passion and he said he'd looked at him because he was going to be a
hunchback. He cried himself into a fever and was ill all
night." "If he ever gets angry at me, I'll never go and see him again," said Mary
heun have thee if he wants thee," said Martha thou may as well know that at the
start." Very soon afterward a bell bell rang and she rolled up her
knitting. "I dare say the nurse wants me to stay with him a bit," she said. "I hope
he's in a good temper." She was out of the room about 10
minutes and then she came back with a puzzled expression. "Well there has bewitched him,"
she said. "He's up on his sofa with his picture books He's told the nurse to
stay away until 6:00 I'm to wait in the next room the minute she was gone he
called me to him and says, 'I want Mary Lennox to come and talk to me, and
remember you're not to tell anyone You'd better go as quick as you can." Mary was
quite willing to go quickly. She did not want to see Colin as much as she wanted
to see Dickon, but she wanted to see him very much. There was a bright fire on the
hearth when she entered his room, and in the daylight she saw it was a very
beautiful room indeed.
There were rich colors in the rugs and hangings and pictures and books on the
walls which made it look glowing and comfortable even in spite of the gray sky and falling
rain. Colin looked rather like a picture himself. He was wrapped in a velvet
dressing gown and sat against a big brocaded cushion. He had a red spot on each
cheek. "Come in," he said. "I've been thinking about you all
morning." "I've been thinking about you, too," answered Mary. "You don't know how
frightened Mara is. She says Mrs. Medlock will think she told me about you and
then she will be sent away." He frowned. "Go and tell her to come here," he
said. "She is in the next room." Mary went and brought her back. Poor Martha was
shaking in her shoes. Colin was still frowning. "Have you to do what I please or
have you not?" he demanded. "I have to do what you please, sir," Martha faltered,
turning quite red. "Has Medlock to do what I please?" "Everybody has, sir," said Martha.
"Well, then, if I order you to bring Miss Mary to me, how can Medlock send you away
if she finds it out?" "Please don't let her, sir," pleaded Martha. "I'll send her away if
she dares to say a word about such a thing," said Master Craven
grandly. "She wouldn't like that, I can tell you." "Thank you, sir," bobbing a curtsy,
"I want to do my duty, sir." "What I want is your duty," said Colin more grandly still.
"I'll take care of you. Now go away." When the door closed behind Martha, Colin
found Mistress Mary gazing at him as if he had set her
wondering. "Why do you look at me like that?" he asked her. "What are you thinking
about?" "I am thinking about two things." "What are they? Sit down and tell
me." "This is the first one," said Mary, seating herself on the big stool. "Once in
India I saw a boy who was a Raja He had rubies and emeralds and diamonds stuck
all over him. He spoke to his people just as you spoke to Martha. Everybody had to
do everything he told told them— —in a minute. I think they would have been killed if they
hadn't." "I shall make you tell me about raja's presently," he said, "but first tell
me what the second thing was." "I was thinking," said Mary, "how different you are from
Dickon." "Who is Dickon?" he said. "What a queer name!" She might as well tell him, she
thought. She could talk about Dickon without mentioning the secret garden. She
had liked to hear Martha talk about him.
Besides, she longed to talk about him. It would seem to bring him
nearer. "He is Martha's brother. He is 12 years old," she explained. "He is not like
anyone else in the world. He can charm foxes and squirrels and birds just as
the natives in India charm snakes. He plays a very soft tune on a pipe and
they come and listen." There were some big books on a table at his side and he
dragged one suddenly toward him. "There is a picture of a snake
charmer in this," he exclaimed. "Come and look at it." The book was a beautiful one
with superb colored illustrations and he turned to one of them. "Can he do that?" he asked
eagerly. "He played on his pipe and they listened," Mary explained. "But he doesn't
call it Magic. He says it's because he lives on the m so much and he knows
their ways. He says he feels sometimes as if he was a bird or a rabbit himself, he
likes them so. I think he asked the robin questions. It seemed as if they talked to
each other in soft chirps." Colin lay back on his cushion and
his eyes grew larger and larger and the spots on his cheeks
burned. "Tell me some more about him," he said. "He knows all about eggs and nests,"
Mary went on. And he knows where foxes and badgers and otters live. He keeps
them secret so that other boys won't find their holes and frighten them. He
knows about everything that grows or lives on the mo Does he like the mo said Colin. "How
can he when it's such a great, bare, dreary place?" "It's the most beautiful place,"
protested Mary. "Thousands of lovely things grow on it and there are
thousands of little creatures all busy building nests and making holes and
burrows and chipper or singing or squeaking to each other. They are so busy
and having such fun under the earth or in the trees or heather. It's their
world." "How do you know all that?" said Colin, turning on his elbow to look at
her. "I have never been there once, really," said Mary suddenly remembering. "I only
drove over it in the dark. I thought it was hideous. Martha told me about it
first and then Dickon. When Dickon talks about it you
feel as if you saw things and heard them and as if you were standing in the
heather with the sun shining and the gors smelling like honey— —and all full of bees and
butterflies." "You never see anything if you ill," said Colin
restlessly. He looked like a person listening to a new sound in the distance
and wondering what it was. "You can't if you stay in a room," said
Mary. "I couldn't go on the more he said in a resentful tone. Mary was silent for
a minute and then she said something bold. "You might—
—sometime." He moved as if he was startled.
"Go on the more How could I I? I am going to
die." "How do you know?" said Mary unsympathetically. She didn't like the
way he had of talking about dying. She did not feel very
sympathetic. She felt rather as if he almost boasted about it. "Oh, I've heard it
ever since I remember," he answered crossly. "They are always whispering about
it and thinking I don't notice. They wish I would, too." Mistress Mary felt quite
contrary. She pinched her lips together. "If they wished I would," she said,
"I wouldn't. Who wishes you would?" "The servants— —and of course Dr.
Craven because he would get mleth and be rich instead of poor. He Daren say so, but
he always looks cheerful when I am worse.
When I had typhoid fever his face got quite fat. I think my father wishes it,
too." "I don't believe he does," said Mary quite obstinately.
That made Colin turn and look at her again. "Don't you?" he said. And then he lay
back on his cushion and was still, as if he were thinking. And there was quite a
long silence. Perhaps they were both of them thinking strange things children do
not usually think of. "I like the grand doctor from London,
because he made them take the iron thing off," said Mary at last. "Did he say you
were going to die?"
"No." "What did he say?" "He didn't whisper," Colin answered. "Perhaps he knew I hated
whispering. I heard him say one thing quite aloud. He said, 'The lad might live
if he would make up his mind to it. Put
him in the humor.' It sounded as if he was in a
temper." "I'll tell you who would put you in the humor, perhaps," said Mary
reflecting. She felt as if she would like this thing to be settled one way or the
other. "I believe Dicken would. He's always talking about live things. He never talks
about dead things or things that are ill. He's always looking up in the sky to
watch birds flying— —or looking down at the earth to see something
growing. He has such round blue eyes and they are so wide open with looking about.
And he laughs such a big laugh with his wide mouth— —and his cheeks are as red— —as
red as cherries." She pulled her stool nearer to the sofa and her expression quite
changed at the remembrance of the wide curving mouth and wide open eyes. "See
here," she said. "Don't let us talk about dying; I don't like it. Let us talk about
living. Let us talk and talk about Dickon.
And then we will look at your pictures." It was the best thing she could
have said. To talk about Dick and meant to talk about the moall and about the
cottage and the 14 people who lived in it on 16 shillings a week— —and the
children who got fat on the mor grass like the wild ponies. And about dickens's
mother— —and the skipping rope and the more with the sun on it— —and about pale
green points sticking up out of the black sod. And it was all so alive that
Mary talked more than she had ever talked before— —and Colin both talked and
listened as he had never done either before. And they both began to laugh over
nothing as children will when they are happy together. And they laughed so that
in the end they were making as much noise as if they had been two ordinary
healthy natural 10-year-old creatures— —instead of a hard, little,
unloving girl and a sickly boy who believed that he was going to die. They
enjoyed themselves so much that they forgot the pictures and they forgot about the
time. They had been laughing quite loudly over Ben Weatherstaff and his robin and
Colin was actually sitting up as if he had forgotten about his week back when
he suddenly remembered something. "Do you know there is one thing
we have never once thought of," he said. "We are cousins."
It seemed so queer that they had talked so much and never remembered this simple
thing that they laughed more than ever, because they had got into the humor to laugh at
anything. And in the midst of the fun the door opened and in walked Dr. Craven and Mrs.
Medlock. Dr. Craven started in actual alarm and Mrs. Medlock almost fell back
because he had accidentally bumped against her.
"Good Lord!" exclaimed poor Mrs. Medlock, with her eyes almost starting out of her head. "Good
Lord!" "What is this?" said Dr. Craven, coming forward. "What does it
mean?" Then Mary was reminded of the boy Raja again. Colin answered as if neither the
doctor's alarm nor Mrs. Medlock's terror were of the slightest
consequence. He was as little disturbed or frightened as if an elderly cat and
dog had walked into the room. "This is my cousin, Mary Lennox," he
said. "I asked her to come and talk to me.
I like her. She must come and talk to me whenever I send for her." Dr. Craven turned
reproachfully to Mrs.
Medlock. "Oh, sir," she panted. "I don't know how it's happened. There's not a servant
on the place that dare to talk— —they all have their orders."
"Nobody told her anything," said Colin, "she heard me crying and found me herself. I
am glad she came. Don't be silly, Medlock." Mary saw that Dr. Craven did not
look pleased, but it was quite plain that he dare not oppose his patient. He sat
down by Colin and felt his pulse I'm afraid there has been too much
excitement. Excitement is not good for you, my boy," he said. "I should be excited
if she kept away," answered Colin, his eyes beginning to look dangerously
sparkling. "I am better. She makes me better. The nurse must bring up her tea
with mine. We will have tea together." Mrs. Medlock and Dr. Craven
looked at each other in a troubled way, but there was evidently nothing to be
done. "He does look rather better, sir," ventured Mrs. Medlock. "But"— "—thinking the matter
over—" —"he looked better this morning before she came into the
room." "She came into the room last night.
She stayed with me a long time. She sang a Hindustani song to me and it made me
go to sleep," said Colin. "I was better when I wakened up. I wanted my breakfast. I
want my tea now. Tell nurse, Medlock Dr. Craven did not stay very long.
He talked to the nurse for a few minutes when she came came into the room and
said a few words of warning to Colin. He must not talk too much; he must
not forget that he was ill; he must not forget that he was very easily
tired. Mary thought that there seemed to be a number of uncomfortable things he was not to
forget. Colin looked fretful and kept his strange black lashed eyes fixed on Dr.
Craven's face. "I want to forget it," he said at last. "She makes me forget it. That
is why I want her." Dr. Craven did not look
happy when he left the room. He gave a puzzled glance at the little girl
sitting on the large stool. She had become a stiff, silent child again as
soon as he entered and he could not see what the attraction was. The boy actually
did look brighter, however— —and he sighed rather heavily as he went down the
corridor. "They are always wanting me to eat things when I don't want to," said
Colin, as the nurse brought in the tea and put it on the table by the sofa. "Now,
if you'll eat I will. Those muffins look so nice and hot. Tell me about
rajas CHAPTER 15 NEST